in Dublin. (Laughter) But she's on her way. This is the last piece. This is about the supposed arrival at the sum of all of our endeavors. In Santiago itself -- it could be Santiago, it could be Mecca, it could be Varanasi, it could be Kyoto, it could be that threshold you've set for yourself, the disturbing approach to the consummation of all your goals. And one of the difficulties about walking into your life, about coming into this body, into this world fully, is you start to realize that you have manufactured three abiding illusions that the rest of humanity has shared with you since the beginning of time. And the first illusion is that you can somehow construct a life in which you are not vulnerable. You can somehow be immune to all of the difficulties and ill health and losses that humanity has been subject to since the beginning of time. If we look out at the natural world, there's no part of that world that doesn't go through cycles of, first, incipience, or hiddenness, but then growth, fullness, but then a beautiful, to begin with, disappearance, and then a very austere, full disappearance. We look at that, we say, "That's beautiful, but can I just have the first half of the equation, please? And when the disappearance is happening, I'll close my eyes and wait for the new cycle to come around." Which means most human beings are at war with reality 50 percent of the time. The mature identity is able to live in the full cycle. The second illusion is, I can construct a life in which I will not have my heart broken. Romance is the first place we start to do it. When you're at the beginning of a new romance or a new marriage, you say, "I have found the person who will not break my heart." I'm sorry; you have chosen them out unconsciously for that exact core competency. (Laughter) They will break your heart. Why? Because you care about them. You look at parenting, yeah? Parenting: "I will be the perfect mother and father." Your children will break your heart. And they don't even have to do anything spectacular or dramatic. But usually, they do do something spectacular or dramatic -- (Laughter) to break your heart. And then they live with you as spies and saboteurs for years, watching your every psychological move, and spotting your every weakness. And one day, when they're about 14 years old, with your back turned to them, in the kitchen, while you're making something for them -- (Laughter) the psychological stiletto goes in. (Applause) And you say, "How did you know exactly where to place it?" (Laughter) And they say, "I've been watching you for -- (Laughter) a good few years." And then we hope that our armored, professional personalities will prevent us from having our heart broken in work. But if you're sincere about your work, it should break your heart. You should get to thresholds where you do not know how to proceed. You do not know how to get from here to there. What does that do? It puts you into a proper relationship with reality. Why? Because you have to ask for help. Heartbreak. We don't have a choice about heartbreak, we only have a choice of having our hearts broken over people and things and projects that we deeply care about. And the last illusion is, I can somehow plan enough and arrange things that I will be able to see the path to the end right from where I'm standing, right to the horizon. But when you think about it, the only environment in which that would be true would be a flat desert, empty of any other life. But even in a flat desert, the curvature of the earth would take the path away from you. So, no; you see the path, and then you don't and then you see it again. So this is "Santiago," the supposed arrival, which is a kind of return to the beginning all at the same time. We have this experience of the journey, which is in all of our great spiritual traditions, of pilgrimage. But just by actually standing in the ground of your life fully, not trying to abstract yourself into a strategic future that's actually just an escape from present heartbreak; the ability to stand in the ground of your life and to look at the horizon that is pulling you -- in that moment, you are the whole journey. You are the whole conversation. "Santiago." "The road seen, then not seen the road seen, then not seen the hillside hiding then revealing the way you should take the hillside hiding then revealing the way you should take, the road dropping away from you as if leaving you to walk on thin air, then catching you, catching you, holding you up, when you thought you would fall, and the way forward the way forward always in the end the way that you came, the way that you followed, the way that carried you into your future, that brought you to this place, no matter that it sometimes had to take your promise from you, no matter that it always had to break your heart along the way: the sense the sense of having walked from deep inside yourself out into the revelation, to have risked yourself for something that seemed to stand both inside you and far beyond you, and that called you back in the end to the only road you could follow, walking as you did, in your rags of love and speaking in the voice that by night became a prayer for safe arrival, so that one day one day you realized that what you wanted had actually already happened and long ago and in the dwelling place in which you lived before you began, and that and that every step along the way, every step along the way, you had carried the heart and the mind and the promise that first set you off and then drew you on, and that and that you were more marvelous in your simple wish to find a way you were more marvelous in your simple wish to find a way than the gilded roofs of any destination you could reach you were more marvelous in that simple wish to find a way than the gilded roofs of any destination you could reach: as if, all along, you had thought the end point might be a city with golden domes, and cheering crowds, and turning the corner at what you thought was the end of the road, you found just a simple reflection, and a clear revelation beneath the face looking back and beneath it another invitation, all in one glimpse all in one glimpse: like a person like a person or a place you had sought forever like a person or a place you had sought forever, like a bold field of freedom that beckoned you beyond; like another life like another life, and the road the road still stretching on." (Applause) Thank you. Thank you very much. Thank you. You're very kind. Thank you. (Applause)
en Dublín. (Risas) Pero está en camino. Esta es la última pieza. Se trata de la supuesta llegada a la cima de todos nuestros esfuerzos. En Santiago mismo, podría ser Santiago, podría ser La Meca, podría ser Varanasi, podría ser Kioto, podría ser ese umbral que te has propuesto, el enfoque perturbador para la consumación de todos tus objetivos. Y una de las dificultades para entrar en la propia vida, para entrar en este cuerpo, en este mundo por completo, es empezar a darse cuenta de que has fabricado tres ilusiones perdurables que el resto de la humanidad ha compartido desde el principio de los tiempos. La primera ilusión es que de alguna manera se puede construir una vida en la que uno no es vulnerable. De alguna manera uno puede ser inmune a todas las dificultades y enfermedades y pérdidas a las que la humanidad ha estado sujeta desde el principio de los tiempos. Si miramos el mundo natural, no hay parte de ese mundo que no pase por los ciclos del nacimiento, inicialmente, o del ocultamiento, y luego el crecimiento, la plenitud, para comenzar entonces una maravillosa decadencia y luego una desaparición muy austera y plena. Miramos eso, decimos: "Es hermoso, pero ¿puedo tener la primera mitad de la ecuación, por favor? Y cuando ocurra la desaparición cerraré los ojos y esperaré a que llegue el nuevo ciclo". Lo que significa que la mayoría de los humanos están en guerra con la realidad el 50 % del tiempo. La identidad madura es capaz de vivir el ciclo completo. La segunda ilusión es, construir una vida en la que no quiero romper mi corazón. El romance es el primer lugar donde empezamos a hacerlo. Al comienzo de un nuevo romance o un nuevo matrimonio, uno dice: "He encontrado a la persona que no romperá mi corazón". Lo siento; uno la ha elegido inconscientemente justamente por esa exacta capacidad. (Risas) Te romperán el corazón. ¿Por qué? Porque te preocupas por ellos. Si uno mira la crianza, ¿sí? "Seré la madre y el padre perfectos". Tus hijos te romperán el corazón. Y ni siquiera tienen que hacer nada espectacular o dramático. Pero por lo general, hacen algo espectacular o dramático (Risas) para rompernos el corazón. Y luego viven con Uds. como espías y saboteadores durante años, viendo cada movimiento psicológico, y detectando todas sus debilidades. Y un día, cuando tienen alrededor de 14 años de edad, de espaldas a ellos, en la cocina, mientras que uno hace algo para ellos, (Risas) entra el estilete psicológico. (Aplausos) Y tú dices: "¿Cómo sabías exactamente dónde colocarlo?" (Risas) Y dicen: "Te he estado observando (Risas) unos cuantos años. Y esperamos que nuestras personalidades blindadas y profesionales impidan que nos rompan el corazón en el trabajo. Pero si uno es sincero sobre su trabajo, debe romper su corazón. Uno debe llegar a los umbrales donde no sabe cómo proceder. No sabe cómo pasar de aquí a allá. ¿Qué hace eso? Nos pone en una relación apropiada con la realidad. ¿Por qué? Porque uno tiene que pedir ayuda. Angustia. No tenemos una opción sobre la angustia, solo tenemos la opción de que nos rompan el corazón personas, cosas y proyectos que nos interesan profundamente. Y la última ilusión es que de alguna manera puedo planear lo suficiente y arreglar las cosas que voy a poder ver el camino hacia el final desde donde estoy de pie, directo al horizonte. Pero, si lo pensamos, el único entorno en el que eso sería cierto sería un desierto plano, vacío de cualquier otra vida. Pero incluso en un desierto plano, la curvatura de la Tierra alejaría el camino. Por lo tanto, no; uno ve el camino, y después no y luego lo ve de nuevo. Así que esto es Santiago, la supuesta llegada, que es una especie de retorno al principio todo al mismo tiempo. Tenemos esta experiencia del viaje, que está en todas nuestras grandes tradiciones espirituales, de peregrinación. Pero solo al estar realmente en el suelo de la vida, y no absortos en un futuro estratégico que en realidad es solo un escape de la angustia actual; la capacidad de permanecer en el suelo de la vida y mirar el horizonte que nos llama, en ese momento, uno es el viaje entero. Uno es la conversación entera. "Santiago". "El camino visto, luego no visto el camino visto, luego no visto la ladera que se esconde y luego revela el camino que uno debe tomar el camino que se aleja de ti como si te dejara caminando en el aire, y luego te atrapa, te atrapa y te sostiene cuando pensabas que caerías, y te sostiene cuando pensabas que caerías. Y el camino a seguir el camino a seguir siempre, al final, el camino por el que viniste, el camino que seguiste, el camino que te llevó a tu futuro, que te trajo a este lugar, no importa si a veces te trajo una promesa, no importa si siempre te partió el corazón en el camino: el sentido el sentido de haber caminado desde lo más profundo de ti mismo hasta llegar a la revelación, de haberte arriesgado por algo que parecía estar dentro de ti y mucho más allá de ti, te llevó de nuevo al final al único camino que podías seguir, caminando como lo hiciste, con tus harapos de amor y hablando con una voz que por la noche se tornó oración por una llegada segura, para que un día te dieras cuenta de que lo que querías que ocurriese realmente ya había ocurrido hace mucho tiempo y en la casa en que vivías antes de comenzar, y que y que cada paso en el camino, en cada paso a lo largo del camino, habías llevado el corazón, la mente y la promesa que primero te expulsó y luego te atrajo, y que y que eras más maravilloso en tu simple deseo de encontrar un camino y eras más maravilloso en tu simple deseo de encontrar un camino que los techos dorados de cualquier destino que pudieses alcanzar. Eres más maravilloso en ese simple deseo de encontrar un camino que los techos dorados de cualquier destino que pudieses alcanzar: como si desde el principio hubieses pensado el punto final como una ciudad con cúpulas doradas, y multitudes exultantes, y al doblar la esquina en lo que pensabas que era el final del camino, encontraste solo un simple reflejo, y una clara revelación bajo el rostro que mira hacia atrás y debajo de él otra invitación, todo de un vistazo todo de un vistazo: como una persona como una persona o un lugar que buscabas desde siempre como una persona o un lugar que buscabas desde siempre, como un audaz campo de libertad que te llevó más allá; como otra vida como otra vida, y el camino el camino que sigue extendiéndose". (Aplausos) Gracias. Muchas gracias. Gracias. Muy amables. Gracias. (Aplausos)